Wertheimer, Barbara Research Files 5729
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Barbara Wertheimer Research Files
1914-1982
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wertheimer, Barbara
5729
12 cubic feet
12 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection consists mostly of research materials for a monograph she was working on at the time of her death. The tentative title for this book was "Our Century, Our Time" and was to be about working women in America from 1914 to 1983.
3338466
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 26, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 28, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Barbara Mayer Wertheimer (1926-September 23, 1983) was an American labor historian and labor organizer from the 1940s through the early 1980s.
From 1947 to 1948 Ms. Wertheimer was an organizer and acting education director for the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. She worked briefly for the American Labor Education Service and then from 1961 to 1966 as a consultant for the New York State Division of Housing and Community Renewal. In 1966 Ms. Wertheimer joined the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University. While at Cornell she was a senior extension associate, director of the Trade Union Women's Studies program, and, from 1977 on, an associate professor and director of the Institute for Women and Work, which she cofounded. Ms. Wertheimer remained at Cornell until her death in 1983.
Ms. Wertheimer is well known for her monograph "We Were There: The Story of Working Women in America" (1977).
Other Finding Aids
A finding aid arranged by subject is available in PDF form here. Please note: this is a fairly large file and may take some time to load.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4015: Barbara Wertheimer Office Files 5736: Barbara Wertheimer Additional Files 5736 P: Barbara Wertheimer Photographs 6144: Barbara Wertheimer Additional Files 6144 AV: Barbara Wertheimer Collection of Audio Recordings
Women in trade-unions--United States.; Wertheimer, Barbara Mayer,1926-1983
3338466
- Blacks-Gen.-Completed (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Black Work Experience S. Koester (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Finished Material, Blacks WWI (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Health and Safety (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Nursing 1900 to 1920, 1900-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Protective Laws - WWI (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Railroads, 1914-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Special Industries - WWI (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1914 to Present - Statistics (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Strikes 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Statistics - WWI (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Unions - WWI (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Wages and Hours (Box 1, Folder 13)
- WTUL (Box 1, Folder 14)
- War Industries - WWI (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bio's Individual (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Immigrants (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Blacks 1918-1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Depression (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Household Workers 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Employment 1918-1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Equal Rights 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- General - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Garment Industry 1918-1933 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Labor Education - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Organizing - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Protective Laws 1918-1933 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Non Traditional Jobs - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Suffrage (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Women in WWI and 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Occupational Health and Safety (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Southern Workers 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Special Industries 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Statistics - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Strikes 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Unions - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Wages 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Women's Bureau (Box 2, Folder 7)
- UWCH (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Blacks 1930 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Depression (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Employment - 1930s (Box 2, Folder 11)
- General 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Household Workers 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Labor Education 1930s (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Legislation, 1933-1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Organizations - 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Southern Workers 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Nursing 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Occupational Health and Safety 1933-1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Special Industries 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Statistics - 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Occupations 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Strikes 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Unions - 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- White Collar - 1933-45, 1933-1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Working Conditions (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Wages 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- WTUL - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Women's Charter, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- WTUL 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Blacks WWII (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Armed Services WWII (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Aviation (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Child Care (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Employment WWII (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Homework 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Special Industries WWII (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Unions - WWII (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Wages - WWII (Box 3, Folder 11)
- War Industries WWII (Box 3, Folder 12)
- General WWII (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Women in World War II (Box 3, Folder 14)
- WTUL 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Blacks 1945-1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Woman's Bureau WWII Frieds Miller (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Employment and Unemployment (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Equal Pay (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Equal Rights (Box 3, Folder 20)
- General 1945-1964 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Household Workers 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Health and Safety 1940 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Labor Education 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- The Southern School for Workers 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Legislation 1945-1964 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Women in Work - Miscellaneous FF27 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Occupations 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Organizations 1945-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Public Employment 1945-1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Railroads 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Southern Women 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Special Industries 1945-1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Statistical Info 1945-1964 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- WTUL 1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Unions 1945-1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Unions - Meat Packing (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Post War Problems - 1945 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Wages 1945-1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- White Collar Workers (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Bibliography (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Blacks - General 1964-Now (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Changing Hours, Flex Time, Parental Leave, QWL (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Clerical 0 White collar 1964-Now (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Labor Education/Working Women (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Garment 1964-Now (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Women's Bureau Conference, 1945-1950 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Scope and Contents
  April 18 1945, Nov. 10,1950
- Women's Bureau (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Blue Collar 1964-Now (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Unions - General (Box 4, Folder 23)
- General 1964-Now (Box 4, Folder 24)
- ERA and Feminist Activities 1964-Now (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Issues - Current (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Labor Education 1964-Now (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Legislation, Courts, Policies, 1964-Now (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Non-Traditional Jobs 1964-Now (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Occupations - Nursing (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Statistics 1964-Present (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Strikes - Other (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Southern Workers 1964-Now (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Unemployment 1964-Now (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Unions-General (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Unions 1964-Now (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Unions - Amalgamated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Wages 1964-Now (Box 5, Folder 11)
- White Collar Workers 1964-Now (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Women in Labor Force - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Black Women 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Apprenticeship (17), 1979 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Attitudes 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Bibliography 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Blacks (General) 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Blacks in the Work Force 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Blacks - Others 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Blue Collar Workers (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Child Care (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Chronology (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Chemical Workers 70's (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Conferences + Workshops (Box 6, Folder 5)
- The Economy (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Education 70's (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Employment 70's (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Equal Pay (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Equal rights (Box 6, Folder 10)
- FARAH Strike (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Maternity Leaves (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Heads of Families (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Hours of work (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Equal employment (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Household Workers 70's (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Immigrants + Aliens (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Labor Education I (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Labor Education II (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Labor History (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Legislation (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Marriage + Divorce (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Miners 70's (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Native Americans 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Non-Traditional Jobs 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Nursing 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Oral History, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Politics 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Poverty 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Protective Laws, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Public Sector Service (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Safety and Health 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Sexual Harassment (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Southern 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Statistics I (13) (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Statistics II 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Stress 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Strikes (16) (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Technology 1970s (17), 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Trends (18) (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Unemployment and Welfare 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Unions I 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Unions 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Unions J.P. Stevens (22) (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Unions-Women in II 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Wages (2) 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- White Collar Workers 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Work Alienation 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Women in Unions I (6), 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Social Alienation (Box 8, Folder 6)
- 1980 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Abortion (7) 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Aging (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Armed Services 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Attitudes and Issues 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Blacks - General and History 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Blacks in the Work Force 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Blacks and Other Minorities 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Blue Collar Workers 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Clerical Workers 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Communications Workers 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Blacks-Women 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Conference and Workshops 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- The Economy 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Day Care 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Education 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Employment 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Equal Pay 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- ERA 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Equal Rights 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Flight Attendants 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Household Workers 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Hours of Work 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Immigrants and Aliens, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- International Woman's Day (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Home Work (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Foreign Issues 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Native Americans 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Non-Traditional Occupations 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Nursing 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Occupational Hazards (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Organizations (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Pensions 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Postal Workers 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Second Jobs (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Politics, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Poverty (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Reagan (Comics) 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Religions (Box 9, Folder 22)
- Sex Harassment (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Sex Discrimination 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Social Security (Box 9, Folder 25)
- Solidarity Day 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 26)
- Southern (Box 9, Folder 27)
- Statistics 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 9, Folder 28)
- Strikes (Box 9, Folder 29)
- Technology 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Tuition Refund (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Unemployment 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Unions (and South Africa) 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Unions - JP Stevens (6) (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Unions (Women in) (7) (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Unions (9) (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Unions (10) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  Mineworkers United - District 50 (UMW) Newspaper Guild - ANG Packinghouse Workers - UPWA Postal Workers - UFPC Retail Clerks Screen Actors Guild - SAG Service Employees - SEIU
- Unions (4) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  Steelworkers - USWA Teachers -AFT & UFT Transportation - UTU Typographical - ITU Utilities - UWVA
- United Auto Workers 12 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- AFSCME (13) (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Nurses (esp. 1199) (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Flight Attendants (15) (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Wages and Earnings (16) (Box 10, Folder 14)
- White Collar Workers 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Women's Rights (On the Job), 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Working Mothers 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Yale (Unionization of Clericals at) (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Biographies (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Biography - A-C (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Bio's Bloor, Ella (Box 10, Folder 21)
- Ethlyn Christensen Interview - 10/78 - Denver, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Bio's - Day, Dorothy (Box 10, Folder 23)
- Bio's - D-F (Box 10, Folder 24)
- Bio's - G-K (Box 10, Folder 25)
- Bio's - Herstein, Lillian (Box 10, Folder 26)
- Bio - Florence Kelly (Box 10, Folder 27)
- Bio's - L-N (Box 10, Folder 28)
- Bio's - Nestor Agnes (Box 10, Folder 29)
- Bio's Newman, Pauline (Box 10, Folder 30)
- Bio's - O-R (Box 10, Folder 31)
- Bio's - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 10, Folder 32)
- Biography - Karen Silkwood (Box 10, Folder 33)
- Bio's Miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 34)
- Bio's - U-Z (Box 10, Folder 35)
- Lyrics (Box 11, Folder 1)
- To Be Interviewed (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Farm Workers (Box 11, Folder 3)
- 1970's Farmworkers Some 1960 Info., 1970-1979 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Migrant Workers 1914-Present (also Tenant Farmers and Sharecroppers) (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Migrants 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Non-Traditional Jobs (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Latinos - Farmworkers, etc. Chicanas (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Chinese Workers - ACWA & ILGWU Asian American (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Oral Histories U. Michigan/Wayne State A to I (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Oral Histories - U. Michigan/Wayne State M to Q (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Oral Histories - U. Michigan/Wayne State R to Z (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Bibliographies (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Sources - Vol. II (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Sources - Libraries (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Sources - Other (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Books to Look At (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Computer Printouts of Materials from Manila Folders Related to Book (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Chapter Notes from Sept. 1982 (Box 11, Folder 19)
- General Overview - 1914 (Box 11, Folder 20)
- Blacks - General Overview (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Blacks, 1914-1920 (Box 11, Folder 22)
- Clerical 1920s Overview, 1920-1929 (Box 11, Folder 23)
- Movements - Suffrage, Birth Control, 1914-1920 (Box 11, Folder 24)
- Notes: Women in WWI and Strikes to 1920 (Box 11, Folder 25)
- Protective Leg, 1914-1920 (Box 11, Folder 26)
- General 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 11, Folder 27)
- Blacks 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 11, Folder 28)
- Protective Labor Leg 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 11, Folder 29)
- Women Workers and Feminism - Post-Suffrage Movements; Prot. Laws; Liberal-Conservative Battle; Lemons Book, 1920-1929 (Box 11, Folder 30)
- South - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 11, Folder 31)
- Depression - General (Box 11, Folder 32)
- Women - WWII (Box 11, Folder 33)
- General 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 11, Folder 34)
- Current 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 11, Folder 35)
- Photo Ideas(follow-up) (Box 11, Folder 36)
- First National Working Conference on Research: Women in Blue Collar Jobs, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  December 5-6,1974
- Workers' Report on the Condition of Labor and their Effect on Patient Care at San Francisco General Hospital, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  March 1979
- AFL Gompers et al. (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Imperialism/Sp. American War (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Negro Workers and Socialist/Communists (Box 12, Folder 5)
- New Job Areas (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Post-War Impact on Black Workers (Box 12, Folder 7)
- National Labor Union (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Colored National Labor Union (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Migration 1865-1918 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Migration 1918-1924 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Men and General (Box 12, Folder 12)
- General: Black Workers, Men, Women (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Black Work Experience, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Black Work Experience, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- The Depression: General (Box 12, Folder 16)
- Employment Conditions - Urban (Box 12, Folder 17)
- Rural Ag. Conditions (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Workers/Riots (Box 12, Folder 19)
- Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters (Box 12, Folder 20)
- Black Workers in the South, 1914-1929 (Box 12, Folder 21)
- Black Workers - Selected Industries (Box 12, Folder 22)
- Black Workers, 1914-1918 (Box 12, Folder 23)
- Blacks in the Armed Forces (Box 12, Folder 24)
- Black Workers and Related Org. - NACW (Box 12, Folder 25)
- Early NAACP, Urban League (Box 12, Folder 26)
- World War I: General Impact (Box 12, Folder 27)
- Garvey Movement (Box 12, Folder 28)
- The IWW (Box 12, Folder 29)
- The Economic Status of Minorities (Box 12, Folder 30)
- Impact on Black Workers (Box 12, Folder 31)
- Black Workers and the Armed Forces (Box 12, Folder 32)
- Unions and Black Workers, 1941-1945 (Box 12, Folder 33)
- Black Workers and the New Deal (Box 12, Folder 34)
- CIO / Lewis/ Murray et al. (Box 12, Folder 35)
- Black Workers and Organized Labor, 1929-1941 (Box 12, Folder 36)
- NYT/WSJ, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 37)
- Organization: NAACP, Urbanize, CORE and others (Box 12, Folder 38)
- Women and Rights/Workers (Box 12, Folder 39)
- Black Workers in the South (Box 12, Folder 40)
- Black Workers and Education (Box 12, Folder 41)
- Black Workers in Labor Unions (Box 12, Folder 42)
- Civil Rights/Bl. Workers (Box 12, Folder 43)